Finding Aid for Center for Japanese Studies (University of Michigan) Records 1945-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Center for Japanese Studies (University of Michigan) records 1945-2008 1950-2000
University of Michigan. Center for Japanese Studies.
Correspondence, reports, budgets, and other materials concerning the establishment of the Okayama Field Station and the subsequent publication of Village Japan, including correspondence with Douglas MacArthur; also records and minutes, 1947-1987, of the executive committee of the Center for Japanese Studies; also papers relating to the programs and financial operations of the center; and photographs and films.
8742 Bimu C170 2
19 linear feet
27.7 GB online
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was transferred by the Center for Japanese Studies (donor # 3854 ) in various accessions from 1961 to 2008.
The record group is open to research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
The University of Michigan's Center for Japanese Studies (CJS) was established in 1947, and offered its first classes in the fall semester of 1948. The center was one of many "area studies" facilities established at American universities after the Second World War, but was the first such center in the United States that was truly interdisciplinary. The drive for area studies grew out of a sense among American policy makers that a lack of American expertise in foreign language and culture had hindered the U.S. war effort. Area studies centers were intended to remedy this weakness by encouraging intense interdisciplinary scholarship with a strong focus on the mastery of language. The University of Michigan was a logical choice for a Japanese area studies center: it had an established Japanese Studies program (a part of the Oriental Civilization Program) and had housed the Army's Japanese Language School during the Second World War.
The new center was designed to further the academic study of Japan by promoting research, training specialists, and building a research library. From its very beginning, the center was interdisciplinary, drawing faculty from a variety of departments including Oriental language (now Asian Languages), geography, anthropology, and political science. To supplement its classes in Ann Arbor, the center created a field station in Okayama, Japan, in 1950. Scholars at the station pursued original research while immersed in Japanese culture. Village Japan a study by Richard K. Beardsley, John W. Hall, and Robert E. Ward, was the most notable product of this period. Five years later, the center closed the field station, but it continued to support American scholarship in Japan. The center also promoted international scholarship through conferences and visiting professorships.
Most of the area studies centers created in the immediate post-war period, including CJS, were initiated with large grants from the Carnegie Corporation. In 1958, the federal government increased funding of the area centers with the passage of the National Defense Education Act (NDEA). Title VI of that act specifically promoted area and language studies. In the 1970s, however, government and private foundation funding began to dry up, and the center was forced to look elsewhere for funding.
During the 1970s and 1980s, the center became more reliant on funds from corporations and the Japanese government. The Toyota Visiting Professorship, for instance, was established in 1987 with a grant from the Toyota Motor Corporation. The Toyota Visiting Professorship offered students to attend seminars and lectures, as well as attend classes, with world-renowned scholars.
Adapting to the changing needs of students and faculty in the early 1990s, CJS began an afternoon lecture series, which touched on all areas of Japanese culture, economic, and political history. Supplementing the lecture series, is a vibrant film series. The film and lecture series act together for the promotion and dissemination of research about Japan. CJS' website offers extensive resources for students, teachers, and K-14 materials. Currently, outreach efforts include the Japan Technology Management Program, which challenges traditional uses of science and technology, and the continued support of the Asian Library. The library is now the second largest library of Japanese and other Asian language texts in the country.
Directors of the Center for Japanese Studies
1947-1957 Robert Hall
1957-1961 John W. Hall
1961-1964 Richard K. Beardsley
1964-1968 Robert Hall
1968-1971 Roger Hackett
1971-1973 Robert Ward
1973-1974 Richard K. Beardsley
1974-1977 Robert E. Cole
1977-1979 Richard K. Beardsley
1979-1982 Robert E. Cole
1982-1987 John Campbell
1987-1993 Robert L. Danly
1993-1994 Jennifer Robertson
1994-1995 Robert L. Danly
1995-1999 Hitomi Tonomura
1999-2000 Robert Sharf
2000-2002 Hitomi Tonomura
2002-2003 John Lie
2003-2008 Mark D. West
2008- Ken K. Ito
The Center for Japanese Studies records document the founding and functioning of the center, covering the period from the late-1940s through the1990s. The center's executive committee minutes and official correspondence cover most of this period evenly. Otherwise, documentation of the center's history is somewhat uneven. The center's first decade is well covered, with a considerable amount of field research notes and audio-visual material. From the early-1960s on, however, such documentation is sparse. This later period is documented in other ways, though. The records include a considerable amount of material concerning grants and fundraising, and these documents often describe the center's activities in detail. The records pertaining to special activities of the center also cover the later decades well.
The records are arranged in nine series: Administrative Files, Correspondence, Course Material, Faculty Files, Financial, Grants, Research Special Activities, and Audio-Visual Material.
Subjects:
Beardsley, Richard K. (Richard King), 1918---Village Japan.; Cole, Robert E.; Hall, Robert B. (Robert Burnett), 1896-1975; Japan.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; University of Michigan. Center for Japanese Studies.; Villages--Japan--Case studies.; Ward, Robert Elmer.; Japan--Study and teaching.; Okayama-shi (Japan)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Japan.; Hall, Robert B. (Robert Burnett), 1896-1975; University of Michigan. Center for Japanese Studies.; United States. Army. Japanese Language School (University of Michigan); Rice--Japan.; Irrigation farming--Japan.; Japan--Rural conditions.; Okayama-shi (Japan)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; DVDs.
- Administrative Files 1947-1992, 2.5 linear feet
  The Administrative Files series (1947-1991, 2.5 linear feet) consists of minutes of the center's executive committee meetings, staff meeting notes, and meetings and reports evaluating the center's programs. The executive committee minutes cover a wide variety of topics, including funding, appointments, and research. The staff meeting files often concern future plans for the center.
  - 1947-1991
    - Executive Committee Minutes 1947-1987
      - 1947-1983, 9 folders (Box 1)
      - 1983-1987, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Asian Studies Committee 1951-
      - 1951 (Box 2)
      - 1958 (Box 2)
      - 1959 (Box 2)
      - 1960 (Box 2)
    - Study Committee on Undergraduate Courses on Asia 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Administrative Meetings
      - Staff Meetings 1968, 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Asian Studies Faculty Meeting 1979 (Box 2)
      - Korean Studies 1984 (Box 2)
      - Long Range Planning Committee 1976 (Box 2)
    - Evaluating Committees and Reports
      - Analysis of East Asian Language and Area Studies circa 1977 (Box 2)
      - Area Studies Job Development Report 1988 (Box 2)
      - Area Studies Review Committee 1991 (Box 2)
      - Early Material on Area Studies and Japanese Studies 1954-1962 (Box 2)
      - Faculty Advisory Committee on International Programs (FACIP)
        - 1967-1971 (Box 2)
      - International Studies Advisory Council 1989 (Box 2)
      - Japanese Studies in the U.S., Report 1970 (Box 2)
      - Program Evaluation 1976, 1978, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Survey of Japanese Language Students 1985 (Box 3)
      - Year-end Report to the Dean 1974 (Box 3)
    - M.A. Recipients 1946-1988 (Box 3)
    - Office Correspondence and Clippings 1986-1991 (Box 3)
    - Siego, Nagasaki (first Japanese Student at UM, 1873) 1975 (Box 3)
    - Student Fellowship Consideration 1988 (Box 3)
  - 1990-2001
    - Alumni Weekend Banquet June 17, 2000 (Box 18)
    - Army Intensive Japanese Language School Day May 12, 1990 (Box 18)
    - Center Director Orientation 2001 (Box 18)
    - CJS 50th Anniversary 1997 (Box 18)
    - Financial CJS Operating Budget 1993-2008 (Box 18)
    - International Institute, Governing Board
      - January 26, 1996 (Box 18)
      - May 16, 1996 (Box 18)
      - September 18, 1996 (Box 18)
      - June 13, 1997 (Box 18)
      - October 3, 1997 (Box 18)
      - January 30, 1998 (Box 18)
    - Inter-University Center for Japanese Language Studies, Annual Meeting, March 8 and 9 1996 (Box 18)
    - Program for Inter-Institutional Collaboration in Area Studies May 1988 (Box 18)
    - Website Development (Box 18)
- Correspondence 1950-1987, 2 linear feet
  The Correspondence series (1950-1987, 2 linear feet) consists primarily of a log of the center's official correspondence. The correspondence concerns a wide variety of topics, including funding, appointments, research, and conferences.
  - Robert E. Ward 1950 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Unofficial Correspondence 1951-1955 (Box 3)
  - Mischa Titiev 1951 (Box 3)
  - Robert Hall 1951-1952, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - John W. Hall 1952 (Box 3)
  - Adrath Burks 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - Richard Beardsley 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Robert Hall 1954 (Box 3)
  - Robert Ward and Robert Hall 1953-1964 (Box 3)
  - Curtis Manchester 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Dorothy Blair 1954 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re the closing of the Okayama Field Station 1955 (Box 3)
  - Consulate of Japan, Chicago 1973-1976 (Box 3)
  - Center Correspondence Log
    - 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1983-1986, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Center Correspondence Log 1987, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Kyoto Center for Japanese Studies 1987 (Box 5)
- Course Material 1983, 1985-1986
  The Course Material series (1963, 1985-1986, two folders) consists of several syllabi and course descriptions from CJS courses.
  - Syllabi 1963, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Course Descriptions circa 1986 (Box 5)
  - Course Descriptions 1985-2006 (Box 18)
  - Master of Arts, Japanese Studies, Program Handbook 1997-2007 (Box 18)
  - Course Descriptions 2007-2008 (Box 18)
  - Nagara, Susumu Japanese Pidgin English in Hawaii: A Bilingual Description. Hawaii: University of Hawaii Press, 1972 (Box 18)
- Faculty Material 1975-1986
  The Faculty Files series (1975-1986, .25 linear feet) consists primarily of papers memorializing distinguished CJS faculty.
  - Robert Hall
    - Obituaries 1975 (Box 5)
    - Memorial Lecture Series 1975 (Box 5)
  - Robert Beardsley
    - Personal: Resume, Obituaries 1978 (Box 5)
    - Memorial Essay Volume 1983 (Box 5)
    - Memorial Lectures 1986 (Box 5)
  - John Whitney Hall (Box 18)
  - Forrest R. Pitts November 1, 1948 (Box 18)
  - Gary Saxonhouse 2006 (Box 18)
- Financial 1962-1992
  The Financial series (1961-1992, 4.5 linear feet) is divided into three subseries: Budget, Area Studies Funding and Fundraising. The Budget subseries consists of correspondence and reports detailing the budget of the center. The Area Studies Funding subseries consists of correspondence and reports concerning the status of funding for area studies programs. The Fundraising subseries consists of correspondence, proposals and reports concerning fundraising for the center.
  - Budgeting
    - Miscellaneous Financial Papers and Correspondence; mostly re: budget 1963-1968 (Box 5)
    - Budgets 1961-1971 (Box 5)
    - Budget Correspondence 1962-1964 (Box 5)
    - Budget Correspondence and Reports
      - 1972-1974 (Box 5)
      - 1990 (Box 5)
    - Budget Negotiations with College of Literature, Science and the Arts 1983-1992 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Budgets 1985-1992 (Box 5)
  - Area Studies Funding 1970-1984, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Fundraising Correspondence
    - 1973, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Re: Hirohito Honorary Degree 1974 (Box 6)
    - 1974, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Japanese Businesses 1974-1975 (Box 6)
    - 1974-1976, 7 folders (Box 6)
    - Re: Henry Kissinger 1976 (Box 6)
    - 1976, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - 1976, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - East Asian Capital Campaign 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Corporations 1976 (Box 6)
    - General Motors 1976 (Box 6)
    - Corporations 1977 (Box 7)
    - Japanese Corporations 1977-1978 (Box 7)
    - 1976-1992, 16 folders (Box 7)
- Grants 1954-1997
  The Grants (1954-1997, 3 linear feet) series is divided into two subseries: grants to the center and grants by the center. The former consists of correspondence, proposals and reports concerning outside grants to the center. It is organized alphabetically by the name of the foundation, corporation or government bureau administering the grant. The latter consists of correspondence, proposals and reports concerning grants from the center to individual faculty members, and grants to outside researchers requesting funds to use the Asia library. It is organized chronologically.
  - Grants to the Center for Japanese Studies
    - Carnegie Corporation; Reports 1954-1974 (Box 7)
    - Ford Foundation Grant Material 1955-1971 (Box 7)
    - International Education Act 1967 (Box 7)
    - Japan Foundation
      - General Information 1972-1973 (Box 8)
      - Reports and Correspondence 1973-1976, 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Reports and Correspondence 1977-1984, 8 folders (Box 8)
      - Grant Proposal; Naomi Fukuda Bibliography 1983 (Box 8)
      - Grant Proposal 1989 (Box 8)
    - Japanese Government; Grant Money; Correspondence and Press Clippings 1973, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Japan Society; Grant Proposal 1987 (Box 8)
    - Japan U.S. Friendship Commission
      - Japan U.S.-Friendship Act; Lobbying 1971-1972 (Box 8)
      - Library Consortium Grant; Proposal and Reports 1977-1982, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Windows on the Japanese Past: Studies in Archaeology and Prehistory
        - 1980-1983 (Box 8)
        - 1984-1986 (Box 8)
      - Library Consortium Grant 1985-1987 (Box 8)
      - Grant Correspondence 1985-1986 (Box 8)
      - Grant Proposal 1986 (Box 8)
      - On-demand Purchasing Program 1987-1989 (Box 8)
    - Luce Foundation Grant 1977-1980 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Council for the Humanities; Grant Proposal 1983 (Box 8)
    - National Defense Education Act; Department of Education
      - 1959 (Box 9)
      - 1961-1967 (Box 9)
      - 1970-1972 (Box 9)
      - 1974-1978 (Box 9)
      - Title VI Grant Correspondence 1979-1985 (Box 9)
      - Title VI Funding Lobbying 1981-1984, 4 folders (Box 9)
      - Computer Assisted Instruction in Japanese Language Grant Proposals 1985-1987, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - East Asian National Resource Center Proposal 1982 (Box 9)
      - East Asian National Resource Center; Proposals and Reports 1982-1991, 11 folders (Box 9)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities
      - Grant Campaign 1978-1984, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Challenge Grant 1977 (Box 9)
      - Image and Life: 50,000 Years of Japanese Prehistory, Exhibit; NEH funding, 1978-1980 (Box 9)
      - Naomi Fukuda Bibliography Grant 1980-1983 (Box 9)
      - National Science Foundation; "Quality Circles" Study 1981 (Box 9)
      - Rockefeller Foundation; Correspondence re: Kyoto American Studies Seminar (Box 10)
      - U.S. Japan Foundation
        - Grant Proposal 1987 (Box 10)
        - Translation Grant 1982-1983 (Box 10)
        - Naomi Faked Grant 1985-1986 (Box 10)
      - Various companies; Correspondence re Computer Donation 1982-1983 (Box 10)
  - Grants by the Center for Japanese Studies
    - Miscellaneous Grants and Fellowships 1958-1972 (Box 10)
    - Outside Support for Faculty Research 1958-1993 (Box 10)
    - Faculty Research Requests/ Grant Proposals 1974-1982, 7 folders (Box 10)
    - Faculty Research Request/ Grant Proposals 1985-1993, 10 folders (Box 10)
    - Faculty Loan Program 1976-1978 (Box 10)
    - Asia Library Travel Grants 1989-1997, 7 folders (Box 10)
    - FLAS (Foreign Language Area Study) October 1999 (Box 18)
    - Ford Foundation April 1961 (Box 18)
    - Title VI, Department of Education July 2002 (Box 18)
- Research 1950-1979
  The Research series (1950-1979, 1 linear foot) consists of notes and manuscripts relating to research projects, and includes correspondence and other documents relating to the Okayama field research station. Most of the research notes and manuscripts are from the 1950s. The correspondence concerning the field station includes letters from Douglas MacArthur.
  - Okayama Field Station
    - Establishment of Research Center in Japan (Includes Correspondence with Douglas MacArthur) 1947-1960 (Box 10)
    - Establishment of Field Station 1949-1951 (Box 11)
    - Leases of Lands and Buildings (Box 11)
    - Insurance and Taxes (Box 11)
    - Okayama Field Station 1954-1955 (Box 11)
    - Okayama Field Station; Policies and Objectives 1952 (Box 11)
    - Salary Schedules and Personnel (Box 11)
    - Visit of Regent Bonisteel and Dean Niehuss to Okayama Field Station 1954 (Box 11)
    - Work Schedules, Salaries, Taxes (Box 11)
    - Japanese Journal Articles re: Field Station (in Japanese) (Box 11)
  - Village Japan Study
    - Planning, Maps 1957 (Box 11)
    - Public Opinion Surveys 1950-1954 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence 1955-1962 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence and Notes re: Distribution 1959 (Box 11)
    - Reviews 1959-1960, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - "The Relationship of Cultural Patterns and Personality," Interdisciplinary Research Report Directed by Tsuneo Muramatsu 1955 (Box 11)
  - Inland Sea Survey Manuscript 1955 (Box 11)
  - Walnut Grove Study 1977-1979 (Box 11)
- Special Activities 1950-1997, 3 linear feet
  The Special Activities series (1950-1997, 3 linear feet) consists of files concerning a variety of activities that are tangential to the centers primary functions of teaching and researching. The series is arranged alphabetically into 10 subseries: Alumni Material, Conferences, Consultations for Businesses, Faculty Development Seminars, Inter-Collegiate Activities and Organizations, Intra-University Joint Projects, Outreach Programs, Summer Lecture Series, Teachers' Institute in Asian Studies (TIAS), and Visits and Honorary Degrees.
  - Alumni Material
    - Correspondence 1974-1977, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - General Alumni Material and Survey 1981 (Box 12)
  - Conferences
    - 1958-1961 (Box 12)
    - Conference on Modern Japan 1960-1967 (Box 12)
    - State Department Conference on Japanese Area Studies 1962-1963, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Orientalist Congress 1967 (Box 12)
    - American Anthropological Association Conference 1977 (Box 12)
    - Midwest Asian Library Conference 1982 (Box 12)
    - Midwest Japan Seminar; Papers 1987 (Box 12)
    - 10th International Automotive Conference 1990 (Box 12)
    - "Female and Male Role Sharing in Japan," Conference 1991
      - General (Box 12)
      - Electronic Mail (Box 12)
  - Consultations for Businesses
    - Michigan Economic Mission to Japan 1969 (Box 12)
    - Corporate Correspondence 1974 (Box 12)
    - Consultations 1979-1985 (Box 12)
    - Jackson, Michigan, Business Group 1989 (Box 12)
  - Faculty Development Seminars 1964-1967, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Inter-Collegiate Activities and Organizations
    - American Orientalist Society 1985 (Box 13)
    - American School in Japan 1964-1969 (Box 13)
    - Great Lakes College Association
      - Center for East Asian Studies 1973-1975 (Box 13)
      - General 1975-1980, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Lectures 1977-1987, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - Inter-University Center; Reports and Correspondence
      - 1970 (Box 13)
      - 1978-1990 (Box 13)
    - Japan-America Student Conference 1984-1985 (Box 13)
    - Michigan-Chicago Library Consortium 1988-1990, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Midwest Japan Seminar
      - 1970-1971 (Box 13)
      - 1974-1984 (Box 13)
  - Intra-University Joint Projects
    - Asia Library
      - 1976-1980 (Box 13)
      - 1985 (Box 13)
    - Center for Chinese Studies; Joint Programs
      - Publications 1980-1981 (Box 13)
      - General 1988 (Box 13)
    - Office for the Study of Automotive Transportation; Joint Research Effort 1981-1982, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Institute on Labor and Industrial Relations; Japan Study 1982 (Box 13)
    - Lobby Redecoration 1964-1976 (Box 13)
    - Museum of Art, Correspondence 1983 (Box 13)
    - Rackham Graduate School Material 1984-1992 (Box 13)
    - School of Business Administration; Joint MA/MBA Program
      - Correspondence and Reports 1978-1988 (Box 13)
      - "Asian Business: A Student Seminar," Course Pack 1990 (Box 13)
      - "Doing Business in East Asia," Report 1989 (Box 13)
  - History of East Asian Language and Area Studies circa 1977 (Box 14)
  - Survey of Japanese Language Students 1985 (Box 14)
  - Outreach Programs 1983-1995, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Sukiyaki Party 1957-1959 (Box 14)
  - Summer Lecture Series
    - 1956-1961 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence 1957 (Box 14)
    - Clippings 1957 (Box 14)
  - Teachers' Institute in Asian Studies (TIAS)
    - General 1985-1997, 8 folders (Box 14)
    - Coursepack
      - 1993 (Box 14)
      - 1996, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Visits and Honorary Degrees
    - Counsel General Suzula's visit 1973 (Box 14)
    - Ambassador Yasukawa's visit 1973 (Box 14)
    - Saburo Okita Honorary Degree 1973 (Box 14)
    - Emperor Hirohito (Box 14)
      (see folder on 1974 visit in Box 5, fundraising series)
    - Ambassador Togo's Visit 1977 (Box 14)
    - Japanese Music Ensemble 1979-1983 (Box 14)
    - Masaru Ikei, Visiting Professor 1980, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Hitoshi Watanabe, Visiting Professorship 1983-1984 (Box 14)
    - Department of Education Visit 1984 (Box 14)
    - Semba Kaouru, Visiting Musician 1986 (Box 14)
    - Shumpo Akashi, Visiting Artist 1988-1989 (Box 14)
  - Fumon Yoshinori, Satsuma Biwa October 13, 2000 (Box 18)
  - "Japan in the World" Symposium March 9-12, 1988 (Box 18)
    (Japanese language text)
- Audio-Visual Materials 1945-1991, 3 linear feet
  The Audio-Visual series (1945-1991, 3 linear feet) consists of photographs, negatives, slides, reel-to-reel audio tapes, films, a videotape, and cassette tapes. The material dates from the 1950s through the early 1990s. It primarily consists of material about rural Japan recorded for research purposes, and material documenting the social life and educational activities of the Center for Japanese Studies. Some of the films have been duplicated to U-matic videotape.
  - Photographs
    - Album of Photos from Okayama undated (Box 15)
    - Ann Arbor Activities: Students and Staff circa 1945-1967, 1991 (Box 15)
      (includes 1945 photo of Army Japanese Language School)
    - Robert Hall circa 1950-1956 (Box 15)
    - Seto Inland Sea Views (Takashima and Shinotsui) undated (Box 15)
    - Japan Customs and Rituals undated (Box 15)
    - Japan Rural Scenes undated (Box 15)
    - Japanese Festival, Ann Arbor; Ambassador Araki's visit 1952 (Box 15)